If people never did silly things nothing intelligent would ever get done.
Wittgenstein is a drama, history, comedy film directed by Derek Jarman.
A dramatization, in modern theatrical style, of the life and thought of the Viennese-born, Cambridge-educated
philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein, whose principal interest was the nature and limits of language.
A series of sketches depict the unfolding of his life from boyhood, through the era of the first World War, to his
eventual Cambridge professorship and association with Bertrand Russell and John Maynard Keynes.
The emphasis in these sketches is on the exposition of the ideas of Wittgenstein, a homosexual, and an
intuitive, moody, proud, and perfectionistic thinker generally regarded as a genius.
Young Wittgenstein, played by Clancy Chassay.
Ludwig Wittgenstein, played by Karl Johnson.
Betrand Russell, played by Michael Gough.
Lady Ottoline Morrell, played by Tilda Swinton.
Johnny, played by Kevin Collins.
Martian, played by Nabil Shaban.
Wittgenstein is a 1993 experimental comedy-drama film co-written and
directed by Derek Jarman, and produced by Tariq Ali.
An international co-production of the United Kingdom and Japan, the film is loosely based on the
life story, as well as the philosophical thinking of philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein.
The adult Wittgenstein is played by Karl Johnson.
The original screenplay by literary critic Terry Eagleton was heavily rewritten during pre-production and shooting by
Jarman, radically altering the style and structure, although retaining much of Eagleton's dialogue.
The story is not played out in a traditional setting, but rather against a black backdrop
within which the actors and key props are placed, as if in a theatre setting.
The film was originally part of a series of 12 films on the life and ideas
of philosophers, produced by Ali on behalf of Channel Four.
Only four of the scripts got commissioned: Socrates by Howard Brenton,
Spinoza by Ali, Locke by David Edgar and Wittgenstein by Eagleton.
Spinoza was filmed and directed by Chris Spencer as
Spinoza : The Apostle of Reason.
Citizen Locke was filmed and directed by Agnieszka Piotrowska.
These were broadcast in 1994 as 52-minute television films.
The film explores themes of biography, lgbt, gay theme.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.